Doris Caesar Papers
Doris Caesar Papers
1926-1977
Caesar, Doris.
6.0 linear ft.
Spanning 1926 to 1977, the Doris Caesar Papers comprises biographical material, correspondence-subject files, artwork, writings, and memorabilia of the New York-born sculptor (1892-1971). Correspondents include Alexander Archipenko, Alexander Calder, Frank Kacmarcik, William Pachner, and James A. Porter. The collection illuminates Caesar's personal life and the evolution of her artistic career.
148884
Biographical History
American sculptor (1892-1971), specialized in the portrayal of the female figure and saints.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Arranged alphabetically, the Correspondence-subject files (Box 1) consists of incoming letters and outgoing holograph drafts, as well as other documents relating to artwork. Among the correspondents are architect James T. Canizaro; art associations (Atlanta Art Association, Audubon Artists, inc., National Association of Women Artists, Inc.); art dealers (Curt Valentin, Erhard Weyhe); art galleries and museums (Addison Gallery of American Art, Busch-Reisinger Museum of Germanic Culture, Dayton Art Institute, Des Moines Art Center, Grand Rapids Art Gallery, Kalamazoo Institute of Arts, Lawrence Art Museum, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Museu de Arte, Newark Museum, Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, Philadelphia Museum of Art, Portland Museum of Art, Whitney Museum of American Art); artists (Alexander Archipenko, Vernon L. Bobbitt, Alexander Calder, Dorothea S. Greenbaum, Frank Kacmarcik, William Pachner, James A. Porter); and authors and critics (Carlyle Burrows, Geoffrey Bush, Robert M. Coates, Howard Devree, Charles Z. Offin). Other correspondence includes that of clients (Father Judge Mission Seminary, Morris Gross, Rudolph E. Langer, Litchfield Savings Society, Billy Rose, St. Bernard's Church, Saint Gregory's Priory, Saint John's Abbey, Saint Louis Priory, St. Paul's School, Dorothy and James S. Schramm, Saul Solomon, Frank Sommer, Utica Public Library); educational institutions (Albion College, Connecticut College, Grinnell College, Howard University, Syracuse University, Wellesley College, Williams College); museum curators (John I. H. Baur, Henry Bryan Caldwell, Bartlett Harding Hayes, Leona E. Prasse, James L. Whitehead, Carl Zigrosser); photographer Rohn Engh; and typographer Elmer Adler.
Artwork encompasses original sketches, photographs, and reproductions of Caesar's works. Photographs include those of exhibitions (1950-1967) and sculpture, which is subdivided by early works, general works (in alphabetical order by title), and portraits (arranged by name of person).
Autobiographical reminiscences partially documented by photographs, notes on sculpture, published and unpublished poems, and a statement on art constitute Writings. Memorabilia comprises a list of earnings from art sales, photographs, printed material, and scrapbooks. A portrait of Caesar by Willard Warren Cummings, her art studios (1926-1968), and personal life are depicted by Photographs. Printed material includes a book and newspaper clippings about Caesar (1926-1969), exhibition catalogs for group and one-person shows (1931-1969), an exhibition poster from Petit Palais, and reviews of her artwork and poetry (1931-1966). While the originals are restricted in the interest of preservation, photographs and photocopies reproduce Caesar's two Scrapbooks in their entirety (1931-1970).
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Sculptors; Archipenko, Alexander, 1887-1964.; Caesar, Doris.; Calder, Alexander, 1898-1976.; Kacmarcik, Frank.; Pachner, William, 1915-; Porter, James A. (James Amos), 1905-1970.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Christian art and symbolism.; Church decoration and ornament -- United States.; Figure sculpture 20th century -- United States.; Figure sculpture, American.; Human figure in art.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Women artists -- United States.; Women in art.; Women sculptors -- United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Photographs.; Poems.; Reminiscences.; Scrapbooks.; Sketches.; Artists.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
The originals are restricted in the interest of preservation. Photographs and photocopies reproduce Caesar's two scrapbooks in their entirety (1931-1970).
Acquisition Information
Gift of Doris Caesar, 1963-1970.
Inventory
- Biographical Material
  - Biographical Material (Box 1)
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Addison Gallery of American Art (Andover, Mass.), 1941; 1953,; 1957 (Box 1)
  - Adler, Elmer, See Calle del Cristo
  - Albion College (Albion, Mich.), See Bobbitt, Vernon L.
  - Archipenko, Alexander, 1931; undated (Box 1)
  - Atlanta Art Association, 1954; 1955 (Box 1)
  - Audubon Artists, inc., 1961 (Box 1)
  - Baur, John I. H., See Whitney Museum of American Art
  - Bobbitt, Vernon L., 1958; 1960 (Box 1)
  - Burrows, Carlyle, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Busch-Reisinger Museum of Germanic Culture (Cambridge, Mass.), 1958 (Box 1)
  - Bush, Geoffrey, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Calder, Alexander, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Caldwell, Henry Bryan, 1960; 1962 (Box 1)
  - Calle del Cristo (San Juan, Puerto Rico), 1960-1963; undated (Box 1)
  - Canizaro, James T., 1961; 1964 (Box 1)
  - Coates, Robert M., 1956 (Box 1)
  - Connecticut College, 1958; 1960,; undated (Box 1)
  - Dayton Art Institute (Ohio), 1950; 1958 (Box 1)
  - Des Moines Art Center (Iowa), 1964; 1965 (Box 1)
  - Devree, Howard, 1957; undated (Box 1)
  - Engh, Rohn and Jeri, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Father Judge Mission Seminary (Monroe, Va.), 1961; undated; See also Canizaro, James T. (Box 1)
  - Grand Rapids Art Gallery (Michigan), 1960 (Box 1)
  - Greenbaum, Dorothea S., 1939 (Box 1)
  - Grinnell College (Iowa), 1965 (Box 1)
  - Gross, Morris, undated (Box 1)
  - Hayes, Bartlett Harding, See Addison Gallery of American Art
  - Howard University (Washington, D. C.), 1958 (Box 1)
  - Kacmarcik, Frank, 1959-1964; undated (Box 1)
  - Kalamazoo Institute of Arts (Michigan), 1965 (Box 1)
  - Langer, Rudolph E., 1950 (Box 1)
  - Lawrence Art Museum (Williamstown, Mass.), See Williams College
  - Litchfield Savings Society (Connecticut), 1950 (Box 1)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N. Y.), 1951 (Box 1)
  - Museu de Arte (Sao Paulo, Brazil), 1958; 1959 (Box 1)
  - National Association of Women Artists, Inc., 1953; 1960 (Box 1)
  - Newark Museum (New Jersey), 1950; 1958,; 1977 (Box 1)
  - Offin, Charles Z., 1939; 1951,; 1952 (Box 1)
  - Pachner, William, undated (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1953; 1958 (Box 1)
  - Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1949; 1958 (Box 1)
  - Porter, James A., See Howard University
  - Portland Museum of Art (Maine), 1958; 1960 (Box 1)
  - Prasse, Leona E., 1962 (Box 1)
  - Rose, Billy, 1955; undated (Box 1)
  - St. Bernard's Church (Hazardville, Conn.), 1955; 1959,; 1962 (Box 1)
  - Saint Gregory's Priory (Three Rivers, Mich.), 1964-1966; undated (Box 1)
  - Saint John's Abbey (Collegeville, Minn.), 1959-1965; undated (Box 1)
  - Saint Louis Priory (Creve Coeur, Mo.), 1962; 1964-1965,; undated (Box 1)
  - St. Paul's School (Concord, N. H.), 1964; undated (Box 1)
  - Schramm, Dorothy and James S., 1960; undated (Box 1)
  - Solomon, Saul, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Sommer, Frank, 1953; 1959,; 1962 (Box 1)
  - Syracuse University, 1964-1965; 1969,; undated (Box 1)
  - Utica Public Library (Utica, N. Y.), 1958 (Box 1)
  - Valentin, Curt, 1941; 1954 (Box 1)
  - Wellesley College (Massachusetts), 1953 (Box 1)
  - Weyhe, Erhard, 1945-1965; undated (Box 1)
  - Whitehead, James L., 1959-1964 (Box 1)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art (New York, N. Y.), 1951-1961 (Box 1)
  - Williams College (Williamstown, Mass.), undated (Box 1)
  - Zigrosser, Carl, See Philadelphia Museum of Art
  - A-Z, 1 folder
- Artwork
  - Original drawings and sketches (mixed pencil-charcoal-watercolor-pastel), 65 items; mainly nudes and figures (Oversize 1-2)
  - Photographs
    - Exhibitions, 1950-1967 (Box 2)
    - Sculpture
      - Early works (untitled) (Box 2)
      - General
        - By title - A-R, 6 folders (Box 2)
        - By title - S-Z, 5 folders (Box 3)
        - Untitled, See also Memorabilia: Photographs: Art Studios (Box 3)
        - Oversize photos of sculpture (Oversize 3)
  - Portraits (by name of person) - A-Z (Box 3)
  - Reproductions, 1933-1969; undated (Box 3)
- Writings
  - Autobiographical reminiscences - holograph (Box 4)
  - Autobiographical reminiscences with photographs - holograph (Box 4)
  - Notes on sculpture, 1951-1968, undated; Incorporates photographs, artwork reproductions, sketches, exhibition invitation; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Poems
    - Certain Paths; Phantom Thoughts, 1934; 1937; 2 vols. in boxed set (Box 4)
    - Untitled holograph and typescript statement on art - holograph, undated (Box 4)
- Memorabilia
  - Financial
    - Statement of earnings from art sales, 1958-1963 (Box 4)
  - Photographs
    - Art studios, 1926-1968; undated (Box 4)
    - Artwork by others, Cummings, Willard Warren - portrait of Doris Caesar (Box 4)
    - Personal, 1928; undated; 1961, (Box 4)
  - Printed material
    - Books - Doris Caesar / Martin H. Bush (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1932-1969; undated (Box 4)
    - Exhibition catalogs
      - Group shows, 1942-1964; 7 folders (Box 5)
      - One-person shows, 1931-1969 (Box 5)
    - Exhibition poster - Petit Palais - "New York Six", 1950 (Oversize 1)
    - Reviews, 1931-1966; undated (Box 6)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Originals, 1931-1970; 2 books (Oversize 4)
    - Photographic and photocopied reproductions, 1931-1970; 2 volumes in 2 folders (Box 6)